Hi, this is Matt Baker. A few weeks ago,
I started a new series of charts based
on our popular Tree of Life poster, and
I launched a Kickstarter in order to
start taking pre-orders. Originally, the
plan was to create four new charts, but
today I'm happy to announce that there
will actually be five. That's because
I'm now going to publish a standalone
bird chart as well as a standalone
mammal chart. The other three will be
the same. Plants and fungi,
invertebrates, and fish, amphibians, and
reptiles. One of the reasons I'm doing
this, besides the fact that a lot of
people asked for it, is because we've
now reached our stretch goal on
Kickstarter, which means that everyone
who selected one poster will now get two
at no extra charge. Those who selected
two will now get three, and those who
signed up for the full set will get
five. Now, if you haven't yet signed up
to support the Kickstarter, don't worry
because it's not too late. The project
is live until August 31st. After that,
you'll still be able to pre-order, but
at a slightly higher price. So, if
you're interested in learning more, I
suggest you check out the project page
now by going to
usefulcharts.com/kickstarter
or by clicking the link in the
description or pinned comment. The goal
is to have all of these new charts
designed, printed, and shipped out in
time for the holidays. Now, the other
cool thing about this project is that
I'll be sharing my progress as I go so
that you, the viewer, will be able to
give your input by suggesting things to
either add or change. Last time, I
shared the first draft of the bird
family tree. So, today I'm going to
share the second and hopefully final
draft. I got a lot of great suggestions
about birds to add, and I've managed to
include most of them, as well as several
photos contributed by fans through I
Naturalist. So, what I'm going to do now
is go through the tree again and point
out some of the things I've added.
Okay, first of all, on this new version,
I've made sure to include all 46 orders.
And for each one of those 46, I've also
decided to indicate the number of
species that it holds. So that's what
those little numbers are. Also, since
the new chart is larger, I've
incorporated more colors so that the
tree now starts with purple for
everything below the level of neoavies.
Under the paleogathy, which are mostly
flightless birds, I've added the one
exception to this, the tinnamu, which
can fly, although not very well. I've
also added two well-known extinct
species, the moas from New Zealand, and
the elephant birds from Madagascar. So
like I mentioned last time, paleogathy
literally means old jaws and this is in
direct contrast to all other birds who
belong to neogathy which means new jaws.
The neognathy can be further divided
into galloansery or fowl and the
neoavies or new birds which is where
most birds are found. When it comes to
fowl, I added chacha lakas, oldworld
quail, and several more ducks. For my
animator, Seiaawish, because he loves
ducks. Let's now move over to Neoavies,
which is where things switch to blue,
which is appropriate because this is
where we find a lot of water loving
birds. Although, take note that not all
the birds in this section are water
birds. Like I mentioned last time,
according to the latest DNA research,
the neoavies are now divided into four
sections. The first one, Miranda, I've
now split into flamingos and greaves.
And in the second, calves, I've added
several additional orders. These are
smaller and not very wellnown, but since
I wanted to be comprehensive in terms of
orders, I went ahead and added them. Oh,
and I also split cacul into cuckoo and
roadrunners. Under the third neoav
section, elementaves, the strior or
nightb birds was another area with a
bunch of smaller not very well-known
orders that needed to be added. I'm glad
I did though because this is where we
find some of the most unusual looking
birds such as the frog mouths. Now, two
birds that were requested multiple times
to be added were the shoe bill, which
yeah, I've seen reels of this one.
Totally looks like an animatronic, but
is actually real. And the Watson, which
is one of those strange outliers that
gets its very own order. But one bird
that I can't believe I forgot,
especially considering that I was born
and raised in Atlantic Canada, was the
puffin. It belongs to the Alidi family,
which is where we also find the now
extinct great o from the penguinous
order. As someone pointed out in the
comments, when Europeans saw penguins
for the first time, they were reminded
of this genus, which is why penguins are
called penguins, even though they
actually belong up here in a totally
different order. The final thing new in
this now blue section is the rail family
which also includes coots which look
like ducks but like the stupid Canadian
wolf bird are not actually ducks. They
along with cranes, shorebirds and the
watson are now grouped together in a
cate called grui which means cranelike.
Okay, we now come to the fourth neoavies
section, the teleravies or land birds
which is green like the forest. As I
mentioned last time, we get a major
split here between the Australies which
evolved in Australia and South America
and the Afroavies which evolved in
Africa. In Afroaves, I added a few extra
birds of prey, but it is over here in
the cari morphe that I made the most
changes. Another bird that I can't
believe I forgot to add was the toucan,
which is closely related to woodpeckers.
But there were a lot of smaller, not so
well-known orders that needed to be
added here, too, such as the rollers,
which is where the name of this entire
cate comes from. Now, probably the
biggest change to this entire chart that
I made was that I added a bunch more
Australian birds in addition to opening
up shipping to Australia on the
Kickstarter. Previously, I had mostly
focused on North America and a bit of
Europe, but this time I tried to be more
global in my approach. So, here we find
one of the most famous Australian birds,
the cucura, but we'll find many more
further up. Let's now move over to the
Afroavies and in particular the
paserforms order, which is by far the
largest order of birds. As you can see
here, it contains a whopping 6,75
species, which is more than all of the
other 45 orders combined. So that's why
it is here that we get yet another color
change, this time to yellow. Now, most
birds in paserformis are song birds
belonging to the paser suborder, but a
minority belong to the tanni suborder,
which I expanded a bit as well. Take
note that the name tyranni comes from
the same root as tyrannosaurus because
in both cases these animals are
considered to be tyrants. Now obviously
tyranny birds are nowhere near as scary
as a T-Rex but several of them are known
for fiercely defending their nests
against larger birds. Now previously I
divided the song birds into just
paserites and corvides. But there is
actually another cate here that is
important because it contains a lot of
the most common Australian song birds
such as the fairy rens, honey eataters,
waddle birds and noisy miners. However,
corvides also contains a lot of
Australian birds. So I expanded them
quite a bit as well. So for example,
Australia has a magpie that is different
from the common magpie. It fits in the
Artimite family alongside the Kurowongs
and butcher birds. Then in other
families, we get even more Australian
birds such as fanales, magpie larks, and
birds of paradise. Not the plant, the
bird. Now, personally, my absolute
favorite category of birds are crows.
So, I expanded the Corvvis genus a bit,
too, since I had room. Last time, I
pointed out the American crow. We'll
take note that in the southern US, there
is also a separate species called the
fish crow, which is a bit smaller.
However, when it comes to the
northwestern crow, which is the type of
crow found in my part of the world, the
Pacific Northwest, it is no longer
considered to be its own species, but
rather just a subspecies of the American
crow. Likewise, I incorrectly said last
time that Europe had two main crow
species, the Kerrion crow and the hooded
crow, but they are actually considered
to be the same species. Now, finally, I
added the two main Asian crow species,
the large build crow and the hooded
crow. Okay, let's now head over to the
paserites section, which is where things
switch to orange. First, I made it a bit
more clear that we get three parvders
here. Paserita, Sylvia, and Muskapida.
In all three, I tried to add more
oldworld birds for those of you in
Europe, Africa, and Asia. So, in Sylvia,
I added chiffs, babblers, and bulbles.
And in musky capita, I added nighting
gales and mas. Although, I also added
caturts, which live in the new world,
and wax wings, which live in both.
Finally, in Paserita, I added the
African Quas, which in terms of sheer
numbers is the most common wild bird in
the entire world. I also renamed the New
World 9 primaried oen embryzoida, which
is their official name as a super
family. And I decided to use the final
color red for them in order to help them
stand out. For those of us who live in
North America, this group is special
because it contains most of the song
birds that are endemic to, meaning only
found in the new world as opposed to
oldw world birds like house sparrows and
starings that were brought over during
colonization. Finally, I added as
someone suggested Darwin's finches due
to their special place in the history of
evolutionary theory and because unlike
their name suggests, they aren't
actually a part of the finch family.
Okay, so that's how the bird wall chart
is shaping up. Let me know if you think
any final changes are needed, especially
if you spotted any typos. And if you
haven't yet pre-ordered your copy, be
sure to head over to Kickstarter right
now using the link in the description or
pinned comment. Next up, I'll be working
on the mammal chart. So, keep an eye out
for a video about that sometime soon.
Thanks for watching.